Hi and welcome to living in central
Texas. If you are considering on
relocating to the central Texas area,
Temple, Belton, Celo, or any of the
beautiful neighboring areas and you're
sort of curious on where to start, this
video is for you. Hi, I'm Andrea Dudik,
realtor and associate broker with Vista
Real Estate. And today I'll be walking
you through everything you need to know
if you're looking to move
[Music]
here. So before you start looking at a
ton of homes online or before you book a
flight to come down here and visit,
let's have a call. If we talk first,
I'll be able to really get a good sense
of your overall timeline, budget,
lifestyle, and what truly matters to
you. This can save you a lot of stress,
unnecessary,
um, wasted time, and get you going in
the right direction. So, number two is
going to be narrowing down the area
that's right for you. It's a lot more
than just finding the perfect house. Um,
but relocating is really about choosing
the right area that fits your lifestyle,
commute, and long-term goals. Central
Texas is really interesting because each
area um really has its own personality.
So, for Temple, we know that Temple has
a growing job market, great hospitals,
and new construction developments. There
are a lot of communities within Temple.
I recently did a video on comparing
Temple, Bel, and Celo specifically, and
we find that majority of the houses
actually fall within Temple. Um, but
then you can also be part of the Belton
school district while also living in
Temple. So, by having that call and
finding out your motivation, I'll
actually help you narrow down which
areas, especially if it's school
district related there. Um, Belton. So,
Belton really gives you that small town
vibe. very charming historic seal in
some areas. You also get lake living in
other areas of Belton closer to Morgan's
Point, which I really love. I also did a
full video on Morgan's Point if you want
to go take a look there. There are fewer
homes technically in Belton, but Temple
and Belton, there's a ton of overlap.
City of Belton, Belton ISD, City of
Belton, Belton ISD. Uh, so I I wouldn't
get too hung up there. And I actually
think that you'll probably end up
looking in both areas if you like one or
the other. So is going to feel a little
more artsy, um, a little more upscale.
Houses are a little bit more expensive
price per square foot. You get larger
lots. It's a golf course area community,
so you get you see a lot of people
riding around on golf carts and there's
not as much shopping or dining in that
area, but really you're 20 minutes out
from Temple Beltton. Um, so not too far
away from any amenities, especially if
you're used to traveling at all in
bigger areas. So once we have that call
and we help you narrow down which area
you want to be in, I'll set you up on
the MLS, which is multiple listing
service. That's what we as agents um
organize your search parameters with and
it helps us get very very specific on
what you're looking for. We can make
that kind of broad at first and narrow
that down. But Zillow, Trullia,
Realtor.com, all of those third-party
sites actually pull information from the
MLS. And so the MLS is going to be the
most accurate source for uh finding your
ideal home. Once we get you set up on
there, we can um you know, I'll be able
to check in on you to see if we need to
revise that search criteria at all and
then potentially even look at some
houses even if you're not here. Number
three, we're going to talk resale versus
new construction. We can do you can
narrow that down before or after we set
up your MLS search. Um but this is
something to really have a good
conversation about initially. And you
might not know which which one you want
just yet because quite honestly there
are a lot a a lot of pros and cons for
both. Um you
know there is a ton of inventory in our
market right now and so we're seeing a
few things. Um of course this is subject
to change based on any given day and I
guess time that you watch this video.
But because there is so much inventory
again we are really in that buyer
market. A lot of these builders are
offering
insanely great incentives. So incentives
being things like offering money toward
your closing costs um towards a rate buy
down um since interest rates are on the
higher end of what we've seen histo uh
well not even historically just on the
higher end of what we've seen as of
late. and uh we might get blinds,
fridge, washer, dryer, um design
allowances, things things of that
nature. So, if you're considering new
construction, you may get a steal in
getting a brand new construction home.
Um and a generally those incentives are
for spec homes, which are homes that
have already been started. you're really
not going to get those sort of
incentives if you're looking to do a
custom build or um you know working with
one of those what we call production
builders, those build bigger builders
and going you know start to finish.
Those incentives are generally with
those already started homes and
inventory already on the ground. Not
saying that you won't get any, but
they're just going to be better with
those homes. So, new construction, not
only do you get obviously a brand new
home, but those builders are generally
going to include warranties. So, you'll
depending on the builder, um, and they
will often include things like a
one-year general builder warranty, which
is kind of like a bumperto-bumper
warranty. If anything happens in that
first year, you file a warranty claim
and they get that fixed for you.
Most or a large portion of the builders
will also include a 2-year major systems
warranty, which is your HVAC,
electrical, and plumbing. Texas is hot.
So, if on, you know, year 1.5 your HVAC
system goes out, you've got a warranty
to cover that. Again, all those major
systems. And then just depending, you'll
either get a 10year or a I believe a
6-year foundation warranty. Um, it it
was historically a 10-year foundation
warranty, but the state of Texas just
changed it to, I believe, a six year.
It's either six or seven, but I'm pretty
sure it's a six-year foundation
warranty. So, really great there. Um,
especially if you know you're worried
about maintenance, that can alleviate a
lot of those
concerns. Resale, um, resale are really
great, too. you may have a lot of
negotiation power there especially
because the the sellers are competing
with new construction and the incentives
that they are offering a lot of resale
inventory in our market as well. Um you
know resale homes often sit in more
established neighborhoods. So if big
trees and and inviting and established
communities is a priority to you I'll
often get people that say I don't want a
brand new community. I want a community
that's been loved on for a minute and
has a really established neighborhood.
Maybe that's the direction that you want
to go there. And sometimes those those
more established homes have more
character. They don't feel so cookie
cutter, you know. And I'm not even
saying that that's always the case with
new construction because what you'll
find in Texas is a lot of these builders
really do try to really um hop on design
trends and make every home beautiful.
But you know what I mean. So, you may
already know if you want new
construction or resale when we have that
phone call, and we're able to set you up
on the MLS and search parameters based
on that. If you don't know, we can just
leave it kind of vague so you can see
inventory for both. The next big thing
is getting
prequalified. Um, I like to have this
call first
because, well, for a couple reasons.
If you get pre-qualified, getting
pre-qualified is going to mean speaking
with a lender and seeing how much house
you can afford. And so before you go
looking at houses um that are
$500,000, maybe a lender tells you
you're pre-approved for $600,000 and now
you've opened up your window and you're
excited about looking at things in a
little bit higher price point. Or
alternatively, maybe um you know, debt
to incomewise or situationally
um maybe the lender says based on
parameters you can only afford a
$300,000 house. That is going to shift
obviously which homes you look at. And
one of the worst things you can do is
fall in love with a house and then find
out that you can't afford it or miss out
on a beautiful home that you can afford
that you didn't know you could afford.
Now, getting pre-approved is a generally
pretty quick and simple process. It's
not getting that full stamp of financing
approval. It's really just that initial
approval so we can get started in that
home search. If we submit any offers or
if you submit any offers, a seller is
going to want to see that preapproval
letter. Definitely, definitely,
definitely do that before you start
looking at homes. Now, do that after, in
my opinion, speaking with a realtor. Um,
a second reason for that is because you
always want to use a local lender. Um, I
have some nightmare stories about people
that did not use local lenders. And
generally that falls around the sense
that, perfect example, our while our
home prices are slightly lower than
other areas, if not a lot lower than
some other
areas, our property taxes are higher
than a lot of places. And so if you have
a lender that is not local, they can
make the mistake of qualifying you based
off of a different property tax rate.
What that basically means is your
monthly payment is going to look a lot
different. If they if they estimate
property taxes at a 2.3 rate versus a.7
rate, well, that's hundreds of dollars a
month in your monthly payment, which
changes how much you can afford. So, you
always want to do a local lender because
they know our local market. If I find
out that, for example, you want to go
the direction of a new construction
home, that might change the lender that
I have you speak with, um, or that I
encourage you to speak with because a
lot of these builders provide additional
incentives for using their preferred
lender. So, let's have that call and
let's see which direction you need to
go, but definitely the direction of
getting preapproved regardless. Lastly,
you want to know the process before you
move. It can be very exciting, but also
very scary relocating somewhere you
haven't been to before or maybe you have
been here before and you're just coming
back. But in general, the process can be
strenuous and um a lot. So, I really
think it's important to know the full
process before you move here. When we
have a call, I'll walk you through
everything. So, in ter in addition to
knowing what house you're looking for
and your overall circumstance and
motivations, I'll walk you through the
home the full home buying process. If
you can't get here, we'll discuss what
virtual tours look like and setting up
times time to do that. Um, we'll discuss
the financing pieces of purchasing.
We'll discuss what happens when we
submit an offer. How much money should
you anticipate having upfront for
earnest and option money? Do you know
what those things are? Um, let's we'll
talk inspections and uh just really
everything from start to finish to make
sure that you are so comfortable and so
excited about your move here. Moving
doesn't have to be overwhelming and I
would really love to help simplify the
process. If you would like to book a
free, friendly, low pressure call, you
can find all my contact information
below. If you are not quite ready to
book that call, you can download my free
relocation guide. And don't forget to
subscribe to my channel if you would
like more tips on moving to the central
Texas area. Till next time.